Hello and welcome to our external control,
integrated thermal stimuli in the flow of your experiment webinar.
The webinar will be presented by Gilad Balvilay, Medox R&D manager.
Thank you, Delia. Hello everyone.
Good morning, good evening, wherever you may be in the world.
Let me just bring up the presentation.
So today we'll be talking about external control, which is a software feature of MMS, the MEDOC
main station software.
And we'll be focusing on working using the TSA2, our new device.
TSA2 is a thermal stimulator for those who aren't familiar with it.
used in various applications in clinical work and also in research and today the
application is that we'll be talking about is more focused on research users
who wants to have a multi-modal kind of setup which we'll be talking about. The
TSA2 is used typically for QST.
It has various thermodes which you can mix and match with the system.
We have some upcoming new thermodes that you can see at the bottom here.
As I said, it's a device that you can add thermodes to.
You can have two thermodes.
You can have connectivity with other devices.
And it's easily upgradable.
So, external control is basically a way to connect from an external software, external
code basically, which I'll show you later, to the MMS and it's intended to allow you
to synchronize various devices together.
So if you have a few types of stimulation devices such as visual stimulation, auditory
stimulators and of course thermal stimulators then you can combine that
with an experimental setup that includes recording devices such as an MRI scan
or ECG nerve control sorry nerve conduction and combine that in a setup
that allows you to synchronize all the inputs and outputs together in a
centralized way.
So we typically know of users who are using MATLAB or Python
or V Prime, LabVIEW, et cetera.
So it's any kind of third party code
that you can connect to the system and send commands
in an 8-bit word, basically, which I'll show you later.
And the way it works is it works by having a centralized computer
that could have the MMS installed on it,
connected via USB to the TSA2.
And your code could sit on the same computer.
And then the way it works is it sends the commands
through the network card, and then you
connect to via the local host.
And through that, through this code,
you can control the MMS and also control other devices,
such as an MRI scanner, EEG, et cetera,
and combine a more sophisticated experimental setup.
Another option is to have the same kind of code
and then connect to another computer running MMS over a network and this
allows you some more flexibility. Okay so how does this all work? So the external
control feature in MMS has two stages, two main stages. One stage is the setup
stage and the other stage is the actual listening mode stage which is at the
bottom here. So just as a side comment, in the past, pathway users had this
feature with an LPT serial port or parallel port, sorry, which required some
cable construction and now this is no longer supported and we are only working
with TCP/IP. So let's look into detail of the setup stage. So if you're familiar with MMS,
you know that we have ramp and hold and limits and various types of temperature profile
programs that can be defined. So this is actually the same thing. You create a program that has a
ramp and hold or limits or any other kind of program and then you assign a 8-bit word that
will be used to activate this command and this is done in the external control settings menu so on
the right here in the right pane you can see programs so the program name will be whatever
a program test program that you define and the 8-bit word is customized as you as you can
as you as you want you can just assign any any set of ones and zeros in an 8-bit word on the
left you can see that there are commands that have fixed 8-bit words and they're reserved for those
commands. So it's important to say that we have also situations where there are
multiple users in the lab or in a facility that is using one TSA and each
have their own experimental setup and they can actually save the
configuration of those programs, specific programs that are personalized
to that experiment, customized to that experiment, and that can be saved as a
configuration file and imported/exported, and then there is no interference between
different users and they can not interfere with other people's experiments.
Note that we have an IP address that is detected automatically over here by the
external code to connect.
So if you note on the top here, you have this button,
this checkbox, which should be used to activate,
and I'll show you that.
Activate external control, and I'll show you that in a minute.
So usually in MMS, we have a test subject or a patient
that is defined in MMS.
Usually you can define all the patient details within MMS
but since this feature is typically interfacing
with other devices, it makes sometimes sense
to include patient data or test subject data
outside in the external code.
And you can do that and just call it a test patient,
dummy patient that you can just define in MMS
and then work like that.
Okay, so when you tick the box,
MMS will be in listening mode, not just yet,
only when we select the patient and we go to test mode.
So I'll show you that in a minute.
And then we have the actual working part of the code.
So the code has a command,
set of commands that you can see here and you can start a test, stop a test, call a specific
test and there are other options which you can see just here.
So for example, once you've selected a test that has a response unit functionality such
as limits or search or others a yes response can be simulated by the code and a no response and
uh increased temperature decreased temperature as is in vast search so i'll demonstrate that quite
promptly um so the the mms is actually uh this sort of server and your stone code is a client
and it's sending commands and receiving responses from the mms and you can actually stream out the
data test uh the the time uh temperature and any other command that um is defined here any other
response that is defined here um it's interesting that there is a ttl output not not the input but
the output can be recorded so i'll be showing you how um with the simulated uh f mri that i built
I don't know if you can see this. So we made a small jig that will be used to show you how the MRIs
or any other external recording device can be synchronized with the MMS. Okay, so I'm gonna now
go to MMS. So programs, this is just the default program set and I've defined in
settings in tunnel control you can see that I've defined three programs and I
can select these programs from any of the programs that are already defined and
I've assigned an 8-bit word. So I haven't used any of these, I've defined new ones
and we'll be doing ramp and hold, search and vast search. And this is my IP, I've
ticked the box. I can export this just to my desktop. So this is a
configuration file and this set of programs is now being saved and I can
that later. So let's press OK and go to test. So I've just created a dummy
patient here and when I will press go to test I will have this window. Now this is
the system is now in listening mode and it's waiting for commands. So I'm just
gonna close that for a second and show you an application that made in MATLAB.
So I've made an example in the app and this is something that you can do in any other software,
but just use Matlab for now.
So I've created a main function.
The main function is just formatting the commands and formatting the responses that I want to use
So all of this code package you can get from us,
we can send that to you.
Just send us an email, and we'll be happy to do that.
So I'm showing you now the commands
that you've seen in the table previously.
So we have 14 commands at the moment.
So the status is basically getting a response from the MMS.
The command that you define with this zero code is--
basically, I've defined a response message that
includes the whole output of the response.
The response message is a 23-byte word.
Maybe I'll try and show you that in a second.
So the response is segmented in this way.
Basically, you can have the first four bytes
are the length of the message, the next four bytes
are the timestamp, et cetera, and you can output all of these.
But you need to define that.
So that's the way we did it here.
OK.
So in my app here, it's just a few lines of commands
that I'm sending and receiving,
but you can create any kind of graphical user interface
that is customized to your experiment with buttons, et cetera.
So you can automate your experiments.
So I'm going to now go to listening mode by pressing test.
Maybe I'll minimize the window for a second.
And I'll put that on the side like so so you can see well.
and we'll go to test. So now we're waiting for MATLAB to do something. So I'm just
gonna connect quickly, put in this code and I'll send the command and oops that's
not what we wanted. So in MATLAB I received already this response which
includes the 23-byte message and all of these can be, this means I've connected
already, all of these can be outputted and actually streamed. So if I now create
this sort of loop that is every 50 milliseconds will output a status command
and get a response we can see that the data is being streamed and you can see
the temperature is being changed in real time in time of course and you can also
record this and output it to any kind of file according to file so while that's
doing that, I'm going to bring up the MMS and send a command that will start. I'm using
command number one and the first parameter is the 8-bit word for the ramp and hold. So
I'll do that. Am I connected? I think it's running so I have to stop it.
So let's do this.
And the reason I had to stop it is because I was taking up the sending simultaneous commands
and that would slow, that would, I would need to interrupt the command that's already running.
So let's start the test. So command number two is start test, retest, and start test.
And now I'm waiting for a trigger. So I'm going to hold up my
TTL box or MRI box and send the trigger command which is
this command number four and I don't know if you can see this every time you see a dot or an
asterisk on the screen it's outputting a TTL out command and that can also be seen in this
light being led light being shown
yeah you can see this i hope i hope you can see that so um i've just defined a few um
few points the the start of the of the rise the duration of set a temperature event here
the end of duration, et cetera.
So you can define any point on the graph
that can serve as a reference.
Just to comment, when you load a test,
so I selected this command,
it takes a few seconds, about five seconds
for MMS to load that.
And after that, the latency, the time it takes
for messages to go across should be around
10, 20 milliseconds, depending on your net
connection. Okay so I'm gonna stop this test. You can also pause it before if you want.
Stop the test. Now let's load another program, Search. Search is a program
usually used for identifying a certain temperature point. For example we've seen
I mean users have a sort of tonic temporal summation method which is the patient needs
to press the yes or no buttons to maintain a certain pain level and you see that the
graph looks quite interesting.
It actually, you see where habituation is happening, etc.
So it's quite a useful modality, useful program.
So I've selected that.
Let's start it.
And this test program can be used with the response unit.
So I'm just going to wait for it to reach the destination
temperature.
And now I'm going to start to press yes and then press no.
Press yes again, create this sort of interesting profile that can be predefined in your code.
So now after pressing no, it will continue to decrease until I release the response unit,
the virtual response unit button, which is key up, key up command, and then you can see
that it can stabilize.
And I can raise it up again.
And now it's returning to baseline.
So between this point and this point is the duration that I defined within MMS for search.
So you can actually increase that time as you like and then create the profile within that
time frame.
So let's now stop the test and go to the next program, which is VASC search.
VASC search is a program used usually to go to a certain temperature and ask the patient
what their pain level is and then sort of zero in on what temperature, what the threshold
temperature for pane 60 or any other criterion.
So let's start this test.
Starting, so this is a triggered program.
So I'm gonna trigger it.
And then it's asking me what the step size for the next,
next,
so I'm gonna increase temp by 500, meaning five degrees.
So 500 here is actually multiplied by 100, the actual temperature, and then you can have
a 0.01 precision within external control.
So the next temperature I'm going to decrease by 10.
Let's trigger that.
I decreased it by 1000, meaning 10.
And you can see that it's dropped from--
what is this, around 38 to 28.
The next time, I'm going to increase temp back by 5.
And trigger that.
And then you can have this kind of profile,
which is selecting different thresholds
in different situations.
Of course, pain rating can also be added.
There are more commands, such as next sequence,
and you can play around with that.
Let's stop the test.
And this is actually the end of that demonstration.
So I'm going to go back to my presentation now.
And please, if you have any questions,
I'll be happy to answer at the end.
When is this useful?
So when you're combining visual stimulation with a painful or non-painful thermal stimulation.
For example, there was an experiment where the experimenter was wearing a white coat and
showed the patient's green screen.
And when the green screen is shown, the patient is told that they will receive non-painful
stimulation and when the screen is red, they will receive a painful stimulation.
And this is an example of when you have...
You can use placebos, nacebos, shams, etc., which are helping you to conduct psychological
and pain experiments.
The advantage here is when you want to have an experiment that has a double blind definition,
The way to do that, if you would not have this automation feature within the code, is
that you would need to press buttons, and then you lose sort of the double blind.
The experimenter is not blinded because he has to activate things based on what is the
next stimulus based on what is going to happen.
It is possible to do randomized testing inside MMS, but this just makes it a bit more automated
and comfortable.
Okay, now this is just a few examples of papers.
And I think now we'll be ready to take your questions.
So let's go back to...
Stop sharing.
And let's see if we have any questions and no we don't have any questions.
Okay so just to sum up we have an email info@medoc-web.com which you are free to
contact us and oh we have a question so you're free to contact us and then we
We can send you the example code and any other questions you may have and help with your
experiment and help with the code.
We'll be happy to do that.
We have a question, can this function be used on pathway?
Yes, it can.
Actually I think started on pathway and the TSA2 is slowly replacing the pathway in terms
of the device that is mainly used for research and yes it can.
Okay, so thank you very much. Thank you for your time and we'll be in touch.